Kunal Deshmukh

+91 9075155483 | kunaldeshmukh5245@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/kunal-deshmukh-a94b69179

PROFILE

Data Engineer with 4 years of building experience in large-scale data pipelines, ETL processes, and data warehouse solution. Technologies used such as Python, SQL, Pyspark, Databricks, Synapse, Kafka, ADF to develop multi-terabyte data solution for lifescience domain.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, SQL

Big Data Technologies: Spark, PySpark, Spark SQL

Streaming Technology: Kafka, Azure Event Hub, Spark structured streaming

Cloud computing: ADF, Databricks, ADLS, Amazon S3, Synapse

Orchestration: Airflow Familiar: Fast Api

EXPERIENCE

Infosys Limit

Dec 2024 – Present

Senior Associate Consultant

Banglore, Karnataka

- Developed a real-time data ingestion pipeline using Azure Event Hub to stream high-volume event data.
- Implemented Python-based consumers to read and process events from Event Hub efficiently.
- Integrated with PostgreSQL for intermediate staging and lookup operations during event processing.
- Loaded processed data into Delta Lake tables for scalable and ACID-compliant storage and querying.
- Optimized event processing for high throughput and low latency in a production environment.
- Implemented File, DataBase comparison system to efficiently maintain data consistency between 2 systems.

Tata Consultancy Services

Oct 2022 - Dec 2024

System Engineer

Banglore, Karnataka

- Expertly engineered and optimized ETL processes from various sources, ensuring seamless data consolidation, cost efficiency, and strict adherence to data standardization.
- Designed and orchestrated third-party vendor file pipelines into GDNA using Apache Airflow, optimizing data ingestion workflows, and ensuring smooth loading into Amazon Redshift for real-time analytics.
- Conducted performance tuning on SQL queries, optimizing data retrieval by 20%.
- Developed an Excel-based solution for generating outbound data for table operations, streamlining the data export
 process, and enhancing data handling efficiency.
- Upgraded Databricks Runtime to 13.3, resolving complex ETL issues, and created automated ETL processes to minimize manual efforts for future upgrades.

Tata Consultancy Services

Aug 2021 – Oct 2022

Assistant System Engineer

Banglore, Karnataka

- Implemented data quality checks, resulting in a 15% improvement in data accuracy.
- Upgraded Airflow to version 2.7.3, implemented disaster recovery protocols, and automated instance creation with OneCloud API, ensuring continuous production server uptime.

CERTIFICATION AWARDS

Infosys Certified Big Data Engineer Fresco Play MileStone Award (TCS) Elevate Wings Award (TCS)

EDUCATION

RIT

MHSS

Goa, India

Aug. 2017 - May 2021

Bachelor of Computer Science

Goa, India

Senior Secondary school

Aug. 2015 - May 2017